A Guide to the Taconic Foundation records FA407
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Grants, 1958-2010; 1; 76.73 Cubic Feet 172 document boxes (including 1 half-box), 2 oversized flat boxes; 2.02 Gigabytes 35 digital files
  - Association for Neighborhood and Housing Development (Weatherization Proposal), 1980 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    Proposal to the New York City Department of Employment for a weatherization training and work experience program.
  - Association for Neighborhood Development in East Harlem, 1978-1980 (Box 9, Folder 82)
  - Association for the Study of Negro Life and History Inc., 1968 (Box 9, Folder 83)
  - Association of Black Foundation Executives Inc., 1972-1977, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 84)
  - Association of the Bar of the City of New York
    Materials from 1992-1998 concern the Taconic Foundation's support for the Lloyd K. Garrison Student Leadership Program, established in memory of the former Taconic trustee.
    - 1963-1965 (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - 1969-1970, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - 1979, 1992-1993 (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Astella Development Corporation, 1996-1998 (Box 9, Folder 90)
    The Astella Development Corporation, a community development corporation in Coney Island, Brooklyn, received a grant of $10,000 in 1998.
  - Balcom, David, 1993-1996 (Box 9, Folder 91)
    See also Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights under Law for correspondence by Balcom in his capacity as development officer for the organization.
    Correspondence file mainly concerning Balcom's dissertation research on foundation support for the civil rights movement and voter education project. Balcom was also a development officer for the Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights under Law.
  - Baltimore Neighborhoods, Inc., 1960-1962 (Box 10, Folder 92)
  - Bannockburn Elementary School, PTA, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 93)
    Support toward costs of a pilot busing program for children from Washington, DC, schools to Bannockburn Elementary School in Bethesda, MD.
  - BELL Foundation, 1996-1998 (Box 10, Folder 94)
    The BELL Foundation (Building Enterprises for Learning and Living) received a Taconic Foundation grant in 1996 to help launch a tutoring program in five Harlem elementary schools.
  - Bennington-Rutland Opportunity Council, Inc.
    Support of a pre-school and community organization in Danby, Vermont.
    - 1972 (Box 10, Folder 95)
    - 1973 (Box 10, Folder 96)
      Separated Materials
      Photographic material has been separated from the file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
      - Danby Preschool and Mothers' Group, 1972 Summer; 2014:FA407:025; 8 still images (Item 2014:FA407:025)
        Enclosed in report on the Danby Project, 1973 March 12.
    - 1974-1975 (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 10, Folder 100)
    - 1984-1989 (Box 10, Folder 101)
  - Big Sisters, Inc., 1959-1966, 1972, 1988-1989 (Box 10, Folder 102)
  - Blake, Peter, 1972-1973 (Box 10, Folder 103)
    See also Architectural Forum (Whitney): General.
    Blake was editor of Architectural Forum until 1972, when he became editor of Architecture Plus.
  - Boston Foundation, 1967, 1971, 1985 (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Brandeis University: General
    Funding for Center for Human Resources at Brandeis, to disseminate lessons learned from Taconic Foundation efforts in youth employment at the Smokey House Project, the Youth Energy Corps in New York City, and the Youth Resource Development Corporation in Dutchess County, NY; to implement Center for Program and Policy Assistance on youth employment at Smokey House; and to oversee Smokey House worksite training program.
    - 1982-1985 (Box 11, Folder 105)
    - 1986 (Box 11, Folder 106)
    - 1987-1991 (Box 11, Folder 107)
  - Brandeis University: Los Angeles Project, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 108)
    Consultation for Los Angeles Planning Team from Community Development Department and City Council, June 13-14, 1988, conducted by Brandeis Center for Human Resources. Concept Paper on South-Central Los Angeles Urban Worksite Training Program, by Susan P. Curnan.
  - Brandeis University: Transitional Year Program, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 109)
    Support for pre-freshman year program for selected disadvantaged students.
  - Branton, Wiley A.
    In 1984, the Taconic Foundation engaged Branton as a consultant to review various organizations requesting support for their voter education activities. In addition to this review, the file contains his memorial service booklet and Vernon Jordan's eulogy of Branton, who died in 1988. The Taconic Foundation published the eulogy and distributed copies of it. The file includes the distribution lists, along with some letters of acknowledgment.
    - 1984-1985, 1988-1990 (Box 11, Folder 110)
    - (Distribution of Eulogy), 1989 (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Broad Jump, 1979-1980
    One-time grant in support of Prep for Prep program. Later request declined.
    - 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - 1981, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Broadway United Church of Christ, 1969 (Box 11, Folder 114)
    Support for Nigeria /Biafra relief.
  - Bronx Frontier Development Corporation
    Support for neighborhood development program involving composting, land reclamation, and nutritional education.
    - 1977 (Box 11, Folder 115)
    - 1978 (Box 11, Folder 116)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - 1983-1987 (Box 12, Folder 119)
  - B.R.A.S.H. (Bronx Residents to Attain Sponsorship in Housing)
    Support for housing preservation and neighborhood improvement in the Grand Concourse - Morrisania section of the Bronx.
    - 1976-1978 June (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - 1978 July-December (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Bronx River Neighborhood Centers, Inc.
    - 1963-1966 (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - 1967-1973 (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - 1983-1989 (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Bronx 2000. See South Bronx 2000.
  - Brooklyn Botanic Garden, 1997-2002 (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Brooklyn Legal Services Corporation, 1969-1972 (Box 12, Folder 126)
    Corporation B, South Brooklyn Branch. File includes correspondence, 1972, with Bronx Legal Services Corporation B. Taconic Foundation grant supported a project to teach practical aspects of the law to high school sudents in New York City.
  - Brooklyn Public Library Foundation, Inc., 1993-2000 (Box 13, Folder 127)
  - Brooklyn's Haitian Ralph and Good Shepherd Inc. (BHRAGS)
    Grant in support of Project Reading Stepladder.
    - 1983-1984 June (Box 13, Folder 128)
    - 1984 July-1985, 1987-1988 (Box 13, Folder 129)
  - The Brotherhood /Sister Sol, 1999-2006 (Box 13, Folder 130)
    The Brotherhood/Sister Sol offered supportive programs for African American and Latino youth in impoverished neighborhoods in New York.
  - Business and Professional People for the Public Interest (BPI)
    Support for the implementation of the Supreme Court's Gautreaux decision against the Chicago Housing Authority and for BPI's work on behalf of housing integration, affirmative real-estate marketing, and housing mobility.
    The first three files (from 1973-1979 and 1981) also carried Alexander Polikoff's name, and concern funding for a legal assistant to help monitor the implementation of the legal reliefs.
    - (Alexander Polikoff), 1973, 1977 (Box 13, Folder 131)
    - (Alexander Polikoff), 1978 (Box 13, Folder 132)
    - (Alexander Polikoff), 1979, 1981 (Box 13, Folder 133)
    - 1980 (Box 13, Folder 134)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 14, Folder 135)
    - 1984 (Box 14, Folder 136)
    - 1985-1986 March (Box 14, Folder 137)
    - 1986 April-December (Box 14, Folder 138)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 14, Folder 139)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 14, Folder 140)
    - 1991 January-April (Box 14, Folder 141)
    - 1991 May-July (Box 14, Folder 142)
    - 1991 August-December (Box 14, Folder 143)
    - 1992 January-October (Box 14, Folder 144)
    - 1992 November-December (Box 15, Folder 145)
    - 1993 January-July (Box 15, Folder 146)
    - 1993 August-December (Box 15, Folder 147)
    - 1994 January-October (Box 15, Folder 148)
    - 1994 November - 1997 (Box 15, Folder 149)
  - Cambridge Institute (Information Exchange on Community Economic Development), 1969-1972 (Box 15, Folder 150)
    Grant for conference, 1969. Includes 1972 proposal for new quarterly magazine, Ends and Means.
  - Canty, Donald (City), 1966-1973, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 151)
    Canty was director of the Urban Information Center, at Urban America Inc., and editor of City magazine, published by Urban America starting in 1967, by the National Urban Coalition from 1970-1972, and then independently as City Inc. starting in 1973. The Taconic Foundation declined a 1972 request for funding for City Inc.
  - Careers through Culinary Arts Program, Inc. (C-CAP), 2000-2006 (Box 15, Folder 152)
  - Carnegie Hill Neighborhood Conservation Project, 1961-1962 (Box 15, Folder 153)
  - Catholic University of America: Center for National Policy Review, 1970, 1972-1973 (Box 15, Folder 154)
    See also Center for National Policy Review.
    Grant to support monitoring of HUD regulations relating to segregation of federally subsidized housing.
  - Catholic University of America: National Clearinghouse on Revenue Sharing, 1971-1972, 1974 (Box 16, Folder 155)
    The National Clearinghouse on Revenue Sharing was a joint monitoring project sponsored by the Center for National Policy Review (at the Catholic University School of Law), League of Women Voters Education Fund, Center for Community Change, and National Urban Coalition.
  - Catholic University of America: National Clearinghouse on Revenue Sharing, 1975-1977 (Box 16, Folder 156)
  - Center for Community Change: General
    See also files for National Training and Information Center.
    Includes grants in support of Housing Training Information Center, Neighborhood Revitalization Program, National Citizens' Monitoring Project, Coalition on Block Grants and Human Needs, and Housing Trust Fund Project. Files for 1997-2004 relate primarily to the Housing Trust Fund Project.
    - 1969-1971 (Box 16, Folder 157)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 16, Folder 158)
    - 1974 January-May (Box 16, Folder 159)
    - 1974 June - 1976 (Box 16, Folder 160)
    - 1977 (Box 16, Folder 161)
    - 1978 (Box 16, Folder 162)
    - 1979 (Box 16, Folder 163)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 17, Folder 164)
      Grants in continued support of Neighborhood Revitalization Project, January 1980 and 1981.
    - 1982 (Box 17, Folder 165)
    - 1983 (Box 17, Folder 166)
    - 1984 (Box 17, Folder 167)
    - 1985 (Box 17, Folder 168)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 17, Folder 169)
    - 1988 (Box 17, Folder 170)
      Includes testimony from House Subcommittee on Housing and Community Development, Hearing on "Community Development Block Grants (CDBG) and Urban Development Area Grants (UDAG) Displacement," 1988 September 29.
    - 1989-1990 (Box 17, Folder 171)
    - 1991-1993 (Box 17, Folder 172)
      Contents consist of audited financial statements for 1991 and 1992 and published report, 1992, on "25 Years of Community Change."
    - 1994-1998 (Box 17, Folder 173)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 18, Folder 174)
      Contains the Housing Trust Fund Project's "Status Report on Housing Trust Funds in the United States," September 1997; and "CDBG: An Action Guide to the Community Development Block Grant Program" (Housing and Community Development Guidebooks), April 1998.
    - 1998-1999 (Box 18, Folder 175)
      File contains two Housing and Community Development Guidebooks: "HUD's Consolidated Plan: An Action Guide for Involving Low Income Communities," 1998; and "Workbook for Creating a Housing Trust Fund," 1999.
    - 1999 (Box 18, Folder 176)
    - 2000 (Box 18, Folder 177)
    - 2001 (Box 18, Folder 178)
    - 2002 January-June (Box 18, Folder 179)
    - 2002 July - 2004 (Box 18, Folder 180)
  - Center for Community Change: Coalition on Human Needs
    Founded in 1981 as the Coalition on Block Grants and Human Needs, the Coalition shortened its name to Coalition on Human Needs in 1986.
    - 1983 (Box 18, Folder 181)
    - 1984 (Box 18, Folder 182)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 19, Folder 183)
    - 1987 (Box 19, Folder 184)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 19, Folder 185)
    - 1990 (Box 19, Folder 186)
  - Center for Community Change: Housing Trust Fund Project
    The Taconic Foundation supported the Housing Trust Fund Project, headed by Mary Brooks, from its inception in 1986, when it was affiliated with Pratt Institute's Center for Community and Environmental Development. The Center for Community Change assumed sponsorship of the project starting in 1990. Housing Trust Fund materials dating from 1997 and later are found in the general Center for Community Change files.
    See also Box, Folder, Housing Trust Fund Project (Mary Brooks), 1986-1988, for earlier materials relating to the project under the auspices of Pratt Institute.
    - 1990-1991 (Box 19, Folder 187)
    - 1992-1993, 0 Bound Volumes (Box 19, Folder 188)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 19, Folder 189)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 19, Folder 190)
  - Center for Community Development and Preservation, 1982-1985 (Box 19, Folder 191)
    Grant supporting the production of a guidebook on the creation and uses of non-profit housing development corporations.
    See also Housing Action Council.
  - Center for Comprehensive Health Practice, 1990-1994 (Box 19, Folder 192)
    Support for a training program for child care professionals based on an early-intervention "infant school" model. Includes one photograph.
    - Child playing at the Infant School, 1990 December; 2014:FA407:026; 1 still image (Item 2014:FA407:026)
  - Center for Comprehensive Health Practice (Supplementary Material), 1985, 1991 (Box 20, Folder 193)
    File contains "Pregnant Addicts and Their Children: A Comprehensive Care Approach," 1985; and offprint of article by Frederic Suffet and Marcia Lifshitz, "Women Addicts and the Threat of AIDS," 1991.
  - Center for Contemporary Media, 1990, 1993-1994 (Box 20, Folder 194)
    Support for a documentary film on John Lewis and the Civil Rights Movement ("John Lewis: Marching to Freedom Land").
  - Center for Court Innovation, 2006-2007 (Box 20, Folder 195)
    Support for the center's Youth Justice Board.
  - Center for Employment Training, 1994, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 196)
    Requests for support declined.
  - Center for Information on America
    - 1969-1973 (Box 20, Folder 197)
      A note in the file indicates that publications were housed in a separate pamphlet box.
    - 1974-1975 (Box 20, Folder 198)
    - 1976-1981 (Box 20, Folder 199)
  - Center for Intergenerational Reading, 1996 (Box 20, Folder 200)
    File contains only the grant action. The Center, located at New York Technical College, also received grants from the Taconic Foundation in 1987-1988, 1990, and 1992-1994.
  - Center for Law and Social Policy: Women's Rights Project, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 201)
    File contains three letters in support of the center's Women's Rights Project proposal, which is not in the file.
  - Center for Law in the Public Interest (Irvine suit)
    Grant of $12,500 in 1976-1977 in support of the Center's lawsuit against exclusionary zoning practices in Irvine, CA (Orange County Fair Housing Council et al. v. City of Irvine).
    - 1976-1977 (Box 20, Folder 202)
    - 1978-1979, 1982-1984 (Box 20, Folder 203)
  - Center for Metropolitan Action: Inclusionary Zoning Proposal, 1984 (Box 20, Folder 204)
    The Center for Metropolitan Action, at Queens College, was previously known as the Metropolitan Action Institute. The Metropolitan Action Institute was in turn the successor to the Suburban Action Institute.
  - Center for National Policy, 1983-1984 (Box 20, Folder 205)
    Support for the costs of publication of a monograph on employment policy.
  - Center for National Policy Review
    For earlier materials, see Catholic University: Center for National Policy Review, 1970, 1972-1973.
    The Center for National Policy Review was affiliated with the School of Law at Catholic University in Washington, DC, through August 1985.
    Support for programs to monitor fair mortgage lending and fair housing enforcement; for voting rights projects; and for study by the Citizens' Commission on Civil Rights of restrictive voting registration practices.
    - 1978-1979 (Box 21, Folder 206)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 21, Folder 207)
    - 1982-1985, 1988 (Box 21, Folder 208)
  - Center for New Corporate Priorities (CNCP)
    Support for project to combat redlining.
    An oversize special format item has been separated from the file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
    - 1975 January-July (Box 21, Folder 209)
      An oversize item has been separated from the file and assigned a unique separation number, as noted. Requests to access open special formats should reference the unique separation number.
      - Map - "Where the Money Is: Greenbacking and Red-Lining in Los Angeles: Mortgage Lending, Los Angeles County, January-May 1974", 1975; 2014:FA407:001 (Item 2014:FA407:001)
    - 1975 August - 1977 (Box 21, Folder 210)
  - Center for Policy Alternatives
    - 1989-1990 (Box 21, Folder 211)
    - 1991-1994 (Box 21, Folder 212)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 21, Folder 213)
  - Center for Population Options / Advocates for Youth
    Support for sexuality education, pregnancy prevention, and life-planning programs for teens.
    Prior to 1980, the Population Institute had administered the program, but in 1980, the Institute split into two parts and established the Center for Population Options, which focused on adolescent pregnancy prevention programs. The Taconic Foundation transferred its earlier grant award from the Population Institute to the Center for Population Options. The Center for Population Options changed its name in 1994 to Advocates for Youth.
    - 1980-1981 (Box 21, Folder 214)
    - 1982 (Box 21, Folder 215)
    - 1983-1985 (Box 21, Folder 216)
    - 1986 (Box 22, Folder 217)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 22, Folder 218)
    - 1990 (Box 22, Folder 219)
    - 1991 (Box 22, Folder 220)
    - 1992 (Box 22, Folder 221)
    - 1993 January-September (Box 22, Folder 222)
    - 1993 October -1996 (Box 22, Folder 223)
    - (Supplementary Material), 1982-1985 (Box 22, Folder 224)
      Proposals and progress reports for years 1-3 of Life Planning program.
  - Center for Public Representation: Trubek, David
    Support for a Land-Use Representation Project to offer joint legal representation to the Racine Urban League, the Capital Community Citizens (an environmental group in Madison, WI), and the Wisconsin State League of Women Voters.
    - 1974 (Box 22, Folder 225)
    - 1975 (Box 23, Folder 226)
    - 1976-1977, 1979 (Box 23, Folder 227)
  - Center for Summer Learning (Johns Hopkins University), 2007 (Box 23, Folder 228)
    Support for project undertaken in partnership with Public/Private Ventures to improve quality of summer literacy programming for New York City providers Harlem Reviving Baseball in Inner Cities (Harlem RBI) and Groundwork Incorporated.
  - Central Brooklyn Partnership, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 229)
  - Chicago City Missionary Society, 1961-1962, 1965-1966 (Box 23, Folder 230)
    Lawndale Community Services; support for community law program.
  - Chicago Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights under Law (LCCRUL), 1979-1981 (Box 23, Folder 231)
    Support for Exclusionary Zoning Project.
  - Chicago Urban League
    The one item from 1963 concerns a contribution to the Little Rock Urban League, which the Taconic Foundation transmitted through the National Urban League.
    - 1963-1965 May (Box 23, Folder 232)
      - Chart of Chicago Urban League Income, 1955-1965, 1964; 2014:FA407:002 (Box 210, Item 2014:FA407:002)
    - 1964-1965 May (Box 23, Folder 233)
    - 1965 June - 1967 (Box 23, Folder 234)
    - 1968-1971, 1975-1977 (Box 23, Folder 235)
  - Child Development Center, 1959-1961 (Box 23, Folder 236)
  - Child Development Center, 1962-1963, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 237)
  - Children's Defense Fund
    Full title, Children's Defense Fund of the Washington Research Project, Inc.
    - 1973 (Box 23, Folder 238)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 24, Folder 239)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 24, Folder 240)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 24, Folder 241)
    - 1985-1989 (Box 24, Folder 242)
    - (Supplementary Material), 1986-1988 (Box 24, Folder 243)
      Annual reports for 1986-1988.
  - Child Study Association of America, 1957-1959 (Box 24, Folder 244)
  - Child Study Association of America, 1960-1963, 1968 (Box 24, Folder 245)
  - Child Welfare League of America, Inc., 1961-1964 (Box 24, Folder 246)
  - Child Welfare League of America, Inc., 1965-1967, 1970, 1980, 1986-1987 (Box 24, Folder 247)
  - China Institute in America, 1990-1992, 1995-1996 (Box 24, Folder 248)
    Support for program to train immigrant graduate students and scholars to become science and math teachers in New York City public schools.
  - Church of All Nations, 1966-1968 (Box 25, Folder 249)
    Grant of $1,200 awarded to the Church of All Nations, New York City, in support of an educational project conducted in association with Planners for Equal Opportunity.
    On October 24, 1967, the Taconic Foundation considered a request from Planners for Equal Opportunity for $1,200 to cover the deficit from their October 1967 conference, and their request for funding for a study of citizen participation in New York City's vest-pocket housing and rehabilitation program. While the grant was awarded to the Church of All Nations, the entire file concerns Planners for Equal Opportunity, with no other reference to the Church.
    - Planning: Black and White Today, October 1-4, 1967 (Poster), 2014:FA407:003; 2 copies (Box 210, Item 2014:FA407:003)
  - Church of the Master, 1964-1965 (Box 25, Folder 250)
    Support for a Reading Club, a tutoring program for youth in Harlem.
    - Reading Club, 1964-1965; 2014:FA407:027; 2 still images (Item 2014:FA407:027)
      Images of children reading were used in the proposal booklet. Images have come detached from the pages to which they were glued.
  - Citizens' Board of Inquiry into Hunger and Malnutrition in the United States, 1967-1968 (Box 25, Folder 251)
  - Citizens' Commission on Civil Rights, 1994 (Box 25, Folder 252)
    For earlier funding relating to the Citizens' Commission on Civil Rights, see the Center for National Policy Review file for 1988.
  - Citizens' Committee for Children of New York, Inc.
    Files from 2006-2009 concern support for the Securing Every Child's Birthright program.
    - 1962-1964 (Box 25, Folder 253)
    - 1965-1968 (Box 25, Folder 254)
    - 1969-1972, 1977-1978, 1988, 1995 (Box 25, Folder 255)
    - 2006 (Box 25, Folder 256)
    - 2006-2007 (Box 25, Folder 257)
    - 2008-2009 (Box 25, Folder 258)
  - Citizens' Crusade against Poverty, 1967-1968 (Box 25, Folder 259)
    The Taconic Foundation awarded a grant of $5,000 to the Citizens' Crusade, to help fund a board of inquiry into hunger issues. See also the file on the Citizens' Board of Inquiry into Hunger and Malnutrition in the United States.
  - Citizens Housing and Planning Association, Inc.
    Until 1977, the organization was known as the Citizens Housing and Planning Association of Metropolitan Boston, Inc.
    - 1969-1970 (Box 26, Folder 260)
    - 1971-1972 (Box 26, Folder 261)
    - 1974 (Box 26, Folder 263)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 26, Folder 264)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 26, Folder 265)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 26, Folder 266)
    - 1973 (Box 26, Folder 262)
    - 1984 January-July (Box 26, Folder 267)
    - 1984 August-December, undated (Box 26, Folder 268)
  - Citizens Housing and Planning Council, Inc. (New York)